<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - automation</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/feeds/automation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/</id><updated>2020-08-21T08:35:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering and creativity - all under one hat.</subtitle><subtitle>Engineering and creativity - all under one hat.</subtitle><entry><title>We're going live.</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/we're-going-live.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-21T08:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-21T08:35:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-08-21:/stanley-solutions-blog/we're-going-live.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Let the automation begin... Just stand back.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm imagining the sound of an old-school electric motor grinding its way up to nominal
speed. Can you hear it? That low groan trying ever-so-hard to come up to a comfortable
range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose I should step back and introduce myself. I'm Joe Stanley, at the time of writing,
I'm twenty-three years old, and a graduate of the University of Idaho with both a Bachelors
and Masters in Electrical Engineering. I work with Schweitzer Engineering Laboratories (SEL)
in Pullman, Washington. I spend far too much time trying to automate things that would have
been faster to do by hand; but I guess that's engineering. I'm an avid Pythonista, and I'm
always trying to &amp;quot;convert&amp;quot; others into the language. I also spend a great deal of time
developing and maintaining IEC 61131-3 libraries for SEL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have far too many ideas and thoughts, so I think it's time to start sharing them. If it's
somewhere on the scale between sustainability and automation, I'm probably interested in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that I might start sharing thoughts, ideas, projects, and guides here on this
blog. Now, I'm sure you can hear that motor grinding up to speed!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="automation"></category><category term="automation"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="iec61131-3"></category></entry></feed>