<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - capstone</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/feeds/capstone.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/</id><updated>2020-09-10T20:39:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering and creativity - all under one hat.</subtitle><entry><title>Wildfire Prevention with Sound</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/detecting-fires-with-sound.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-10T20:39:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T20:39:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-09-10:/stanley-solutions-blog/detecting-fires-with-sound.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;&amp;quot;Where there's smoke, there's fire...&amp;quot; Right? What about if sound were a part of it too?&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm very pleased to say that I'm helping to support some really exciting research at
the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://uidaho.edu"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt; this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a couple of my classmates worked on
a truly exciting project that utilized some relatively new sensory technology in conjunction
with some wireless network technology (Zigbee radios) to communicate infrasound (below the
audible range for humans) signatures back for scientists to analyze. These signatures will
inform scientists and firefighters, alike, when (and where) a wildfire has started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this was all well and good, but the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mindworks.shoutwiki.com/wiki/Infrasound_in_wildfire"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; lost funding. Yep. Just like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why I'm so excited to be getting involved. We've already got a team of four fantastic
engineers. A mechanical engineer, two electrical engineers, and a computer scientist. With
luck the group will be able to start some fantastic research that could eventually lead to a
truly exciting product that may help wildland firefighters around the country (and around the
world) find fires &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; and with greater accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group is just getting started, but I'm very excited to see where things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-techy-side"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Techy Side&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how is this supposed to work anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we've all heard stories about how animals can sense an impending natural disaster, and
in fact, that's quite true with wildfire. Most wild game (and many domesticated species too)
have much more astute hearing sense. In fact, they can hear the low-frequency sounds that
we're unable to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sensors we're hoping to utilize will allow our digital system to detect the low-frequency
rumble of wild fire, then with digital signal processing, we'll aim to identify audio
signatures unique to wildfire. With this, we'll be able to detect fire!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, the goal will be to create a mesh-network of devices covering the forest floor in
areas such that devices will be able to communicate amongst themselves to precisely locate
the fire, and to report it to the authorities quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="capstone"></category><category term="sound"></category><category term="audio"></category><category term="wildfire"></category><category term="protection"></category></entry></feed>