<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - Capstone</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/feeds/capstone.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/</id><updated>2024-04-30T12:32:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>engineering and creativity - all under one hat</subtitle><entry><title>Updated Wiki Page for Capstone Projects</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/updated-wiki-page-for-capstone-projects.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-01-22T11:42:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-22T11:42:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2023-01-22:/updated-wiki-page-for-capstone-projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've often written about the various bits of project work pertaining to my Engineering Capstones. I'm proud to say that they've made some really impressive steps, and for that I'm both thankful and very proud. But until now, it's been a bit of a mess trying to put all that information in one place. Now, I'm getting better about that!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yes, I've written a bunch of blogposts about the Engineering Capstone project work that students have been conducting at the University of Idaho. If you don't
believe me, or you've forgotten, go take a look at the &lt;a href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/category/capstone.html"&gt;summary of posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of really cool things that they've done in the past, but I've not done the best keeping up with it all and putting it in one &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; place so that
folks can just find the stuff they're interested in. Well, I've finally gotten around to updating my &lt;a href="https://js.wiki/"&gt;Wiki.js&lt;/a&gt; instance to have some nice pages
about all that information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/stanleywiki-capstone-pages.png" width="100%" alt="new wiki, who dis?"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything, it's a "landing place" for most of the other information that's already been culminated. Regardless, it's a nice face-lift!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://wikijs.stanleysolutionsnw.com/"&gt;Go Take a Look!&lt;/a&gt; Then, let me know what you think in the new GitHub comments section, below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Capstone"/><category term="wiki"/><category term="wikijs"/><category term="markdown"/><category term="capstone"/><category term="self-hosted"/><category term="container"/><category term="docker"/></entry><entry><title>Making Progress with Capstones</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/making-progress-with-capstones.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-05-24T15:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-24T15:25:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2022-05-24:/making-progress-with-capstones.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last two years, I've become more involved as a project sponsor for some University of Idaho Engineering Capstone projects, and I'm very excited about their growth. Progress may be slow, but it's incremental, and we're approaching goals, which is always exciting!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Quick! Recap what's being researched...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I'm very thankful that I've been able to sponsor two different projects. A continuation project from
last year's &lt;a href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/hearing-fires-while-seeing-smoke.html"&gt;wildfire detection project&lt;/a&gt;
and a continuation of my own Capstone project, a &lt;a href="http://mindworks.shoutwiki.com/wiki/Biochar_Production_System"&gt;biochar reactor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wildfire Detector (Team FireSense)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've already talked a lot about this project, so I'm not going to do that here. If you'd like to read up on it more, feel free to check out some of the links
above to the articles I've written previously. Otherwise, check out this year's team poster!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/firesenseposter.png" style="width: 100%" alt="Team FireSense Poster"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="http://vjs.zencdn.net/4.0/video.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video id="wildfire-wing-drop" class="video-js vjs-default-skin" controls
preload="auto" width="683" height="384" poster="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/TtT5YzoM5NiC5xy/download/Image%20Final%20Assembly%20ISO.PNG"
data-setup="{}"&gt;
&lt;source src="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/fTjxgg3MYJSZiFb/download/20220426_155354.mp4" type='video/mp4'&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/4EoeExXHspY5Mmt/download?path=&amp;files=PCB_v3_Layout.jpg" style="width: 100%" alt="FireSense PCB"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Pictures and Videos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/Td3bLsJ4qxj6qqy"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/Td3bLsJ4qxj6qqy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/5LpHagXFSzgqSon"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/5LpHagXFSzgqSon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/4EoeExXHspY5Mmt"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/4EoeExXHspY5Mmt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Biochar Reactor (Team Biochargers)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've talked less about this project here in my blog... but there's still quite a bit of information that I've written about it. So...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.. anyway, feel free to leave a comment if you have questions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/biochargersposter.png" style="width: 100%" alt="Team Biochargers Poster"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="http://vjs.zencdn.net/4.0/video.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;video id="wildfire-wing-drop" class="video-js vjs-default-skin" controls
preload="auto" width="683" height="384" poster="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/L29wCAw6xtXJpRz/download?path=&amp;files=Matt%20and%20Kaitlyn%20with%20Reactor%20(Extra%20Insulation).JPG"
data-setup="{}"&gt;
&lt;source src="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/booBGRygP5zFEmb/download?path=&amp;files=00-00%20Full%20Assembly_Final.mp4" type='video/mp4'&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/booBGRygP5zFEmb/download?path=&amp;files=System_Breakdown_GIF.gif" style="width: 100%" alt="System Breakdown"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Pictures and Videos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/KRNrAZidKwwiANC"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/KRNrAZidKwwiANC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/booBGRygP5zFEmb"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/booBGRygP5zFEmb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/pzeaXT55ffTioEE"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/pzeaXT55ffTioEE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/L29wCAw6xtXJpRz"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/L29wCAw6xtXJpRz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/KPN7QkCsZdSqYpq"&gt;https://nextcloud.stanleysolutionsnw.com/s/KPN7QkCsZdSqYpq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Capstone"/><category term="capstone"/><category term="wildfire"/><category term="university"/><category term="research"/><category term="students"/><category term="biochar"/><category term="agriculture"/></entry><entry><title>Sensing Fire in a World Without Water</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/sensing-fire-in-a-world-without-water.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-02-15T18:41:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T18:41:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2022-02-15:/sensing-fire-in-a-world-without-water.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The world we live in is congested with controversy; left-vs-right, masks-vs-maskless, us-vs-them. So many arguments, one thing that we don't need to argue about is that there are parts of the U.S. that don't have much access to water, and that there are parts of the U.S. that also face some real challenges with wildfire.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wildfire, water-shortages, weird-weather; all sounds like some dystopian sci-fi novel, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scary that some of that is appearing across the United States, isn't it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Now, weather you're a "climate change subscriber," or not, I think there's a lot to be said about the challenges the world faces.
If for nothing else, we've got to figure out where to get all that water from, and we need to figure out what we're going to do to help
face the challenges of wildfire in our increasingly populous world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've written in the past about some of the project work that I'm sponsoring at the University of Idaho, and I wanted to highlight that
briefly while also pointing out some interesting things popping up from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's Happening with Water?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really don't have much to say here, but I did want to highlight an article that shows some of the drama of the water shortages that
are appearing across the American Southwest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://archives.stanleysolutionsnw.com/archive/1651029667.381326/output.html"&gt;Read the article (archived in my personal archive server)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Makes me wish there were other ways I could get involved in researching additional technology in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's New&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/firesense-wing.jpeg" style="width: 100%" alt="Wings for Dropping Fire Sensors"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;photo credit: Luke Woods - student research team&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year is my second year acting as the sponsor for a wildfire detection system, and I have to say, I'm stoked. This is a very
exciting project, and has a lot of potential. If you want to read more about the concept or tech, go check out my articles on
&lt;a href="/finding-fire-and-making-it.html"&gt;finding fire and making it&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="/hearing-fires-while-seeing-smoke"&gt;hearing fires while seeing smoke&lt;/a&gt;,
or &lt;a href="/detectinf-fires-with-sound"&gt;detecting fires with sound&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's new and exciting right now, is the team's approach, using inspiration from Mother Nature. They're using some designs for their
drop-payload which were inspired by a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samara_%28fruit%29"&gt;Samara leaf&lt;/a&gt; so they can make the payload
drop in a safe, and controlled fashion. Now, this isn't exactly a novel idea, there's a few others who have done similar things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hackaday.com/2021/08/07/helicopter-seed-robot-can-also-drop-like-a-rock/"&gt;HELICOPTER SEED ROBOT CAN ALSO DROP LIKE A ROCK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn20045-spinning-seeds-inspire-single-bladed-helicopters/"&gt;SPINNING SEEDS INSPIRE SINGLE-BLADED HELICOPTERS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, this is brand new to us, and so far as I'm aware, it's a new way to drop materials as a deployment technique. I'm very proud of
the team's work, and I'm so excited to see where they'll take this project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, I'll be keeping more updates coming; but let's be honest, I'm in charge of the updates, so they might be a bit sparse, or even
a bit all-over-the-place.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Capstone"/><category term="capstone"/><category term="students"/><category term="university"/><category term="research"/><category term="university of idaho"/><category term="wildfire"/><category term="infrasound"/></entry><entry><title>Finding Fire and Making It</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/finding-fire-and-making-it.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-11-25T15:25:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-25T15:25:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2021-11-25:/finding-fire-and-making-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are just too many cool things to research, and thank goodness for the students at the University of Idaho.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you know me, you probably know that it's far too easy to captivate me with what I think is a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, any idea, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm something of a sucker for interesting research topics, and I'm incredibly thankful that there are some
wonderful students and faculty at the University of Idaho who are willing to investigate some of these exciting
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What Ideas are Being Researched?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I'm very thankful that I've been able to sponsor two different projects. A continuation project from
last year's &lt;a href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/hearing-fires-while-seeing-smoke.html"&gt;wildfire detection project&lt;/a&gt;
and a continuation of my own Capstone project, a &lt;a href="http://mindworks.shoutwiki.com/wiki/Biochar_Production_System"&gt;biochar reactor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... What are these wild ideas, anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wildfire Detection System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wildfires are threatening more and more of the western United States each year, and currently, our only way to
detect fire is by sight. Namely by seeing the smoke of a growing inferno. That's often too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wildfire has a fascinating trait where it creates a very low rumble. It's the same audible rumble that wildlife
and livestock respond to and run away from in advance of the flames becoming wild. This sound is typically in
the range between 0~8Hz; a very low-frequency sound which is below our (human) range of hearing. But that
doesn't mean a little technology can't provide value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, that's exactly where we're researching. The idea of the project is to create very small, economical devices
which can pick up this low-frequency sound and make quick determination whether sound is wild&lt;em&gt;fire&lt;/em&gt; or wild&lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt;; a
clear distinction to be made! If we can make small devices that cost around &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(10-\)&lt;/span&gt;15 per unit that can do all this,
we can make hundreds, if not thousands, and distribute them from an aircraft. Then let those little buggers create
their own wireless network and report back to a central base where all of the information can triangulate regions
where the fire has appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;What are the students working on this year?&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year's student group is working on minimizing the hardware design. Last year, the group worked on utilizing a
large development board; a unit that had more peripheral devices than were needed. Things like a dedicated power
management unit, multiple GPS units, and several radio and serial communication ports. That's not to say that last
year's team was bad, only that there's room to improve the design and reduce the circuit's footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year's team is focusing on design from the microprocessor up. They're starting with the processor, and working
out what additional peripherals are needed. But they're also working on the enclosure that's needed. They've taken
inspiration from both last year's team, and a Samara leaf for the enclosure. The plan is that the leaf's natural
spinning nature will provide the basis necessary to make the design fall smoothly and without a damaging the
crucial components inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Biochar Production System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biochar - What is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it's "the poor man's activated carbon." Essentially, it's charcoal, but with some more useful properties.
There's a lot of interest in the academic and agricultural world for using biochar both in agricultural markets
and wastewater realms. There are many who are interested in the ability of biochar to act as a wastewater filter
in large scales, and there are others who are very interested in use of biochar to help act as a topsoil balancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me further explain the benefits here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biochar is a very porous material, since it's what's left from wood after all the other oils and gasses have been
separated from the wood. Because of this porous nature, biochar can both retain water, and allow it to move more
easily through soil. This is really interesting for farmers in regions like the Palouse where the topology flows
across rolling hills and generates a large number of both micro valleys and hills. These regions are prone to low
crop yield in both the valleys and on the tops of hills. It's all to do with water, actually. Too much water in
the valleys, and not enough on the tops of hills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, biochar is very interesting because it can provide the necessary balance to help water pass through the valleys
more easily and retain the water near the tops of those hills. It's very exciting because this material might help
support our farmers to increase their yields to help feed our growing world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;What are the students working on this year?&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team didn't complete a fully-functional biochar reactor, so this year's team is picking up where we'd left off.
They're working on getting the continuous reactor working efficiently so that we can start experimenting more
effectively. I'm very excited about some of the realizations they've made, too! They've made some excellent
observations about efficiently heating the reactor. The team introduced me to the idea of using electric heat
rather than using either a diesel or propane heater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I wasn't convinced, but they pretty clearly demonstrated the ins and outs of why it's such a good idea.
Considering the fact that a diesel heater consumed as much energy as 73 kitchen toasters, whereas the electric
heaters only uses as much energy as 3 toasters, it makes a lot of sense! The students did a terrific job in
demonstrating their findings and selling me on their proposal. In short, I'm very proud of them for their hard
work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recapping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm so very excited to have these students working on these exciting projects, and I'm thrilled to have the
pleasure of sponsoring the projects. In earnest, I often feel a tinge of imposter syndrome about supporting the
projects, because I'm not ever certain that I'm qualified to support them, and I feel that I'd pull resources
away from other groups. So, I'm very thankful to be able to support these projects. I really hope that I'm able
to continue with these projects!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Capstone"/><category term="capstone"/><category term="wildfire"/><category term="university"/><category term="research"/><category term="students"/><category term="biochar"/><category term="agriculture"/></entry><entry><title>Hearing Fires While Seeing Smoke</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/hearing-fires-while-seeing-smoke.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-07-12T20:18:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T12:32:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2021-07-12:/hearing-fires-while-seeing-smoke.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While most of North Idaho is seeing (and smelling) plenty of smoke, I'm looking back over a successful Capstone project and more to come...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've talked to me at all in the past nine months or so, you probably already know that I had the great privilege of sponsoring an Engineering
Capstone project at the University of Idaho. Now, admittedly, it's something of a selfish endeavor as I have far too many "fun things" that I'd like
to explore, and not enough time or energy to do them all. Thankfully, some good faculty members are just as excited about some of these intriguing
projects as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's more, though, as I sit here in North Idaho, surrounded by worsening smoke from many terrible wildfires, I'm reflecting on the project I was
so lucky to sponsor, and how excited I am for its future, and what future students will bring to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/team-firewatch.jpg" width="300" alt="Meet Team Firewatch!" align="right"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what was it? Well, the project in a nutshell was to lay the groundwork for a design of a device which will detect wildfire using infrasonic sound;
that's the sound that's lower than what we can hear - think that death rumble from that old beater car you drove in high-school. No? Just me? Oh...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The infrasonic sound would be detected by an ultra-economical (yeah, cheap) condenser microphone and amplified before being measured by a small
microcontroller responsible for wrapping that data up into a message sent over-the-air back to some central base. But what's to make it more interesting,
this wireless message is to be sent over a mesh network of these devices. Think hundreds... no, thousands of these little devices scattered around the
forest, all taking readings at specific intervals and relaying that information back to us so we can &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; if there's a wildfire starting anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this all sounds familiar, it's probably because I've already &lt;a href="./wildfire-prevention-with-sound"&gt;told you all about it&lt;/a&gt;. This project is one that
was started a few years back at the &lt;a href="https://uidaho.edu/"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt; and was discontinued due to a lack of funding and support. Luckily
the sponsoring professor was still just as interested as I was, so we were able to pick it back up and continue down the road to developing some really
neat tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;This Year's Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this year, we had a team of some really outstanding students from a variety of backgrounds. Meridian, a mechanical engineer; Carlos, a computer
scientist; and two electrical engineers, Cory and Drew. We had the luxury of giving this fantastic team the flexibility of choosing their own path
in terms of the areas they were really interested in researching, which made for a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really impressed by these students and their willingness to work so hard on this project. They produced some really fantastic work, and I get
the pleasure of keeping it! At least... until next year, when we get some more students to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team was able to design a really wonderful and unique enclosure to encapsulate their microcontroller, sensor, antenna, and amplifier circuit. They
were also able to use some clear acrylic tubing to really show off how sharp this thing looks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://images.shoutwiki.com/mindworks/thumb/5/5b/2021_infrasonic_wildfire_detector_finished_enclosure.png/800px-2021_infrasonic_wildfire_detector_finished_enclosure.png" width="500" alt="The Sensor..." align="left" style="padding:10px;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'm not going to go too-deep into the technical specs of this thing, partly because I don't want to type it all out, and partly because the team
has already done such a fantastic job documenting it both in their &lt;a href="http://mindworks.shoutwiki.com/wiki/Infrasonic_Wildfire_Detector"&gt;Wiki page&lt;/a&gt;
and in their &lt;a href="https://gitlab.stanleysolutionsnw.com/infrasound-detector/portfolio-2020-2021"&gt;GitLab repo&lt;/a&gt; (which is one of the services I host!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's Next&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is nowhere near complete (even as cool as that enclosure looks). So I'm already lined up to sponsor a continued Capstone program again this
year (so long as the University will let me!), and I'm very excited to do so. There's certainly a few key things that we still need to work out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power - An obvious concern for any IoT device, and certainly one responsible for such a challenging environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sensor Validation - This years team did a great job bootstrapping their way up, but with luck, next year's team will be able to refine that work into
  something that can prove the validity of the sensor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wireless Mesh Networking - This was something that was really exciting since this year's team was able to find an open-source library to help with
  this challenge, but there's more to be done; especially if the network is going to be anything larger than a few nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enclosure Testing - Anything exposed to the elements needs to be hardened, and this enclosure still needs a little refinement there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, I'm really excited to see where this project continues to grow, and what this next year's group of students will be able to accomplish!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Team Presentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="videowrapper youtube"&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wcGvln6jVRM"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;University of Idaho Mention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, 10.3 million acres were burned by wildfire, up from 4.7 million in 2019. These disasters cause major destruction, yet our primary tool for detecting wildfire is simply smelling smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific world only recently discovered large wildfires generate infrasonic waves, or sound below the frequency of what the average human can hear, under 20 hertz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team of engineering and computer science seniors, Meridian Haas, Cory Holt, Andrew Malinowski and Carlos Santos, are developing a device that uses infrasonic detection and signal processing to detect wildfires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These devices, deployed in batches, can be used to create a communications network to relay detection information to responders along with GPS coordinates and timestamps at regular intervals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The ability to signal to firefighters to pinpoint a wildfire location when it’s still small could help save thousands of acres and homes,” Haas said. “We want to make this device as cheap as possible and have as many as we can.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a long-range and low-power data transmit network, Holt said the team has verified device communication up to 12 miles so far, well past their ½ mile goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team has developed a compact, low-cost, prototype that could eventually be constructed from decomposable materials to reduce environmental impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long-term goal would be to drop these devices on a location by air. Materials testing is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more about this project and all the ways U of I students are pushing the boundaries of science and technology at the VIRTUAL Engineering Design EXPO!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Capstone"/><category term="wildfire"/><category term="iot"/><category term="mcu"/><category term="mesh"/><category term="radio"/><category term="smart-sensor"/><category term="capstone"/><category term="university"/></entry><entry><title>Wildfire Prevention with Sound</title><link href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/detecting-fires-with-sound.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-09-10T20:39:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T20:39:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com,2020-09-10:/detecting-fires-with-sound.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;&amp;quot;Where there's smoke, there's fire...&amp;quot; Right? What about if sound were a part of it too?&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm very pleased to say that I'm helping to support some really exciting research at
the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://uidaho.edu"&gt;University of Idaho&lt;/a&gt; this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a couple of my classmates worked on
a truly exciting project that utilized some relatively new sensory technology in conjunction
with some wireless network technology (Zigbee radios) to communicate infrasound (below the
audible range for humans) signatures back for scientists to analyze. These signatures will
inform scientists and firefighters, alike, when (and where) a wildfire has started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this was all well and good, but the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mindworks.shoutwiki.com/wiki/Infrasound_in_wildfire"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; lost funding. Yep. Just like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why I'm so excited to be getting involved. We've already got a team of four fantastic
engineers. A mechanical engineer, two electrical engineers, and a computer scientist. With
luck the group will be able to start some fantastic research that could eventually lead to a
truly exciting product that may help wildland firefighters around the country (and around the
world) find fires &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; and with greater accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group is just getting started, but I'm very excited to see where things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-techy-side"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Techy Side&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how is this supposed to work anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we've all heard stories about how animals can sense an impending natural disaster, and
in fact, that's quite true with wildfire. Most wild game (and many domesticated species too)
have much more astute hearing sense. In fact, they can hear the low-frequency sounds that
we're unable to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sensors we're hoping to utilize will allow our digital system to detect the low-frequency
rumble of wild fire, then with digital signal processing, we'll aim to identify audio
signatures unique to wildfire. With this, we'll be able to detect fire!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, the goal will be to create a mesh-network of devices covering the forest floor in
areas such that devices will be able to communicate amongst themselves to precisely locate
the fire, and to report it to the authorities quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="capstone"/><category term="sound"/><category term="audio"/><category term="wildfire"/><category term="protection"/></entry></feed>