<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - Development</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/feeds/development.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/</id><updated>2020-09-20T10:26:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>engineering and creativity - all under one hat</subtitle><entry><title>Write a Good Framework - ONCE.</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/write-framework-once.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-20T10:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-20T10:26:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-09-20:/stanley-solutions-blog/write-framework-once.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;We all want that next great application; NOW. And we KNOW that we can just hash out this great new thing. But where does that leave us the next time we want to do the same sort of thing?&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;C'mon, every developer has had that epiphany moment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;I know, I can just write this thing now, and I'll have exactly what I need, and I'll
never need to touch it again; I'll never need to add more to it, and it will never
change.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wish it worked that way, but let's be honest. Projects develop, add scope, change, and
sometimes, they morph into something new entirely. Actually, that's often where great code
comes from. The best projects are the butterflies of the development world. They start as
a simple little caterpillar, but at some point along the line, they change into something
far more elegant and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why I'm writing this plea to developers out there in the &amp;quot;real world.&amp;quot; We know that
you could just write this little thing, but isn't it nice to get the &lt;em&gt;framework&lt;/em&gt; right the
first time so that when you need to revisit that code, it'll be so much easier. Or, better
yet, isn't it better to prepare the project for the &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;next guy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; who comes along to make
your framework into something incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I've devolved into rambling, as usual, but my point is this: when you spend the time
to develop the framework &lt;em&gt;the right way&lt;/em&gt; the first time, you and all of your colleagues will
thank you. It will make things just &lt;strong&gt;that much easier&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had a handful of experiences with this myself. I started on a couple projects at work
where I developed something that I &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; was a great system, and didn't really require
a superior framework. This inevitably saved time in the short-term, but it bit me later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, I recently realized that I was re-writing the same code over, and over,
and over again every time I had to touch the code. In the end, as it seems, I didn't spend
enough time writing the framework to begin, and that hurt me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="here-s-the-takeaway"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Here's the Takeaway:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, we all love just &amp;quot;pulling in&amp;quot; a library that does the &amp;quot;dirty work&amp;quot; for us.
I think it's time that we focus on getting those libraries right from the onset, so we don't
need to keep re-doing our own work, or the work of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd say drop me a note in the comments, but I haven't quite gotten that set up yet. So, for
now, just keep fighting the good fight, and &lt;em&gt;write those libraries!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Development"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="IEC-61131"></category><category term="Development"></category></entry></feed>