<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - DevOps</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/feeds/devops.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/</id><updated>2021-02-14T19:23:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering and creativity - all under one hat.</subtitle><entry><title>Servers in the Basement...</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/jenkins-servers-in-the-basement.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-14T19:23:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-14T19:23:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2021-02-14:/stanley-solutions-blog/jenkins-servers-in-the-basement.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Some people keep their creepy Christmas decorations in their basement. Others keep their continuous integration servers down there too...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img alt="SEL Rugged Computers mounted and ready for work!" src="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/images/jenkinsbasement/IMG_0851.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whelp, I've gone and done it. I've mounted and installed one of my SEL computers
and set it up for running Jenkins!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't going to be a very in-depth article, but I wanted to say that it's
done. The server is mounted with a brand new switch and surge protector (no UPS
for the moment, but perhaps to come in the &lt;em&gt;relatively&lt;/em&gt; near future). They're
networked back upstairs to my little IT closet, and Jenkins is waiting idly for
me to push new code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent Saturday mounting the server, re-routing all the networking, and setting
up my modem to provide access to the servers by way of a reverse proxy. Perhaps
I'll document what that is and how it works, but that might be another article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I got to work standing up a few &lt;cite&gt;pytest&lt;/cite&gt; projects for both &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/engineerjoe440/selprotopy"&gt;selprotopy&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/engineerjoe440/pycev"&gt;pycev&lt;/a&gt;, what's exciting about this though, is the fact that they're set up
now so that they can access the private resources they need for testing, but
they can be kicked off by my commits and pushes to their repositories on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want proof that these new projects are up and rocking? Check out their build
statuses; and before you say anything, yes, I know they're failing right now.
That's because these projects are still in their infancy, and still need some
TLC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://jenkins.stanleysolutionsnw.com/buildStatus/icon?job=PyCEV-CI" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://jenkins.stanleysolutionsnw.com/buildStatus/icon?job=SELProtoPy-CI" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... now I can really start cranking on that code, and Jenkins can do some of
my dirty work to start running the tests for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Gotta love that SEL blue!" src="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/images/jenkinsbasement/IMG_0852.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to restate that I'm very excited to be using some old SEL hardware and
giving it a second lease on life. These computers are rugged, industrial
machines; and I'm getting to put them to work making these projects solid. Not
to mention that these projects are actually tailored to supporting SEL tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. It's nerdy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. I'm still excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. You guessed it; I'll surely be giving more updates moving forward!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DevOps"></category><category term="SEL"></category><category term="CI/CD"></category><category term="Jenkins"></category><category term="Dev-Ops"></category></entry><entry><title>CI/CD On Industrial Grade Hardware</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/jenkins-on-sel-industrial-hardware.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-07T16:19:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T16:19:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2021-02-07:/stanley-solutions-blog/jenkins-on-sel-industrial-hardware.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Run DevOps CI/CD pipelines on industrial equipment with no moving parts? Ok! Sign me up!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yes... I already have too many computers. But with that said, what's a few more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it was only about a month-and-a-half ago that I was writing about Jenkins
running on a Raspberry Pi, but I outgrew that pretty quickly. In reality, I
really just started with it, and basically gave up; but hey! I learned a lot in
that time. So now, I'm upgrading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-new-hardware"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The new hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am something of a hardware graveyard. Old machines come to me to live out the
end of their lives and, eventually, give up the ghost. I managed to get my hands
on some second-hand industrial computers, to do some bidding for me. Namely, I
picked up some old SEL (Schweitzer Engineering Laboratories) SEL-1102 rugged
computers. They're based on an old Intel x686 processor, and don't have anything
special in the memory arena... but they're super solid machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="SEL Rugged Computers to Run my DevOps Pipeline" src="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/images/SEL1102/IMG_0849.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My comment about being a &amp;quot;computer graveyard&amp;quot; might still apply to these
computers too, but well, they've got a lot more life left in them. You see,
these are ruggedized computers designed for installation into some of the most
extreme environments around the world. Rated for harsh operating conditions,
built with no moving parts (that's right, a computer without fans), and a whole
slew of serial ports (16 DB9 ports alone). SEL maintains a 10 worldwide warranty
too; but I'll grant that this warranty is void because these devices were sold
to me secondhand. I bring up this point, however because it really exemplifies
the commitment to quality that SEL brings to the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for those of you who know me well, you'll also know that I &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; for SEL.
So yeah, I do have some bias there; but I've also gotten to see (first-hand) the
quality that we at SEL put into our products, so I'm very proud to have a few of
these machines running at home, and I'm very excited to put them into production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-new-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The new work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these new servers, I'm excited to set them up running Debian (because, yeah,
they will do that - and very well, I might add) to support a Jenkins server. I
plan to use that, and expose it as my primary integration system. With Jenkins
running on these new machines, I'm going to set up a Pi Cluster to offload the
actual pipeline work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I want the main Jenkins server to be just that... the main server. I want
other machines to do all the &amp;quot;dirty work&amp;quot; for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, before you get too carried away with your thoughts; yes, that does mean more
computers. I've already put in an order for a Raspberry Pi cluster, which I'm
very excited about; but that's another article for the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of this excitement also stems from my need to integrate with some SEL relays
serially for testing with my SELProtoPy project. With all of those serial ports
on these computers, I'll be able to tie in to those relays quite nicely to allow
some really solid automated testing. Better yet, with all of that integration,
I'll be able to do some really nice pipelined builds for testing SELProtoPy and
PyCEV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-s-next"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, next on my plate is to get these machines up and running on my network so
that I can access them remotely and start integrating with GitHub actions to
fire off the builds and testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very excited to be putting some SEL equipment to work in my own personal
development practices, so I'm sure I'll have some more updates as I go along!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Putting some SEL Hardware to Work" src="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/images/SEL1102/IMG_0850.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="DevOps"></category><category term="SEL"></category><category term="Industrial"></category><category term="Rugged Computer"></category><category term="Ci/Cd"></category><category term="Development"></category><category term="Server"></category></entry></feed>