<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stanley Solutions Blog - Python</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/feeds/python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/</id><updated>2020-12-21T19:07:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering and creativity - all under one hat.</subtitle><entry><title>GitLab, Jenkins, Python, and the Raspberry Pi!</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/gitlab-jenkins-and-the-rpi.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-21T19:07:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T19:07:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-12-21:/stanley-solutions-blog/gitlab-jenkins-and-the-rpi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first"&gt;I'm finally getting around to setting up some CI/CD systems for my self-hosted GitLab server... About Time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;CI/CD, Dev Ops, Pipelines, Workflows, Automated Deployment&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Think that's enough buzz words to catch the Google SEO engine's eye?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not, I know, but I'm not going to spend anymore time on it at the moment. See,
I've got bigger items to tackle! Namely, getting Jenkins set up on a Raspberry Pi, as
the name of this article so implies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good news for you; I've cut out the &amp;quot;dirty-work&amp;quot; through the magic of &amp;quot;blog-posting.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the work I've been tackling for some of the other open source projects I'm
developing, I need to develop a local (on-premises) continuous integration solution to
effectively slam my code with testing and verification. After all, what's great code
without equally great tests? I need to have the system on-premises for a couple reasons;
the largest of which being the fact that I need access to custom hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
So, why a Pi? A Pi 3-B no less?!&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that's quite simple; actually. It's the only spare computer I have at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now that I've thoroughly introduced you, to my reasoning, and the topic at hand;
let's get into it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installing-jenkins-on-the-pi"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing Jenkins on the Pi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have GitLab set up on an old x86 laptop running Ubuntu Server 20.04, so
for this article, I'm going to focus on setting up Jenkins on a Raspberry Pi, and
getting the basics of the workflow between Jenkins and GitLab running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Start with a fresh Pi (latest build of the RaspberryPiOS). I had a Pi sitting
around with an older build of Raspbian, but that's several years old, and I
really just wanted to start fresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Update the Raspberry Pi. Well, in the spirit of starting fresh, might as well
update the system!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Install Java with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; sudo apt-get install openjdk-11-jre
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Verify Java Version with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; java --version
&lt;span class="go"&gt;openjdk 11.0.9.1 2020-11-04&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;OpenJDK Runtime Environment (build 11.0.9.1+1-post-Raspbian-1deb10u2)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;OpenJDK Server VM (build 11.0.9.1+1-post-Raspbian-1deb10u2, mixed mode)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;At this point, I took some time to get the Python system up to a state that
would be a bit more useful for me. So I installed &lt;cite&gt;pip3&lt;/cite&gt;, and a number of
Python packages. I suppose this could really be done at any point during this
whole process, but I felt like this was the most sensible time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Download and add the Jenkins Key with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; wget -q -O - https://pkg.jenkins.io/debian/jenkins.io.key &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sudo apt-key add -
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Open a new file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; sudo nano /etc/apt/sources.list.d/jenkins.list
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then add the following line and save the file to add the Jenkins repository as
a source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;deb https://pkg.jenkins.io/debian binary/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Next, another good &lt;cite&gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;/cite&gt; is in order, followed by
&lt;cite&gt;sudo apt-get install jenkins&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Using the command listed below, you can grab the initial admin password to get
started:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; sudo cat /var/lib/jenkins/secrets/initialAdminPassword
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Now it's time to navigate to &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;raspberry-pi-ip-address:8080&lt;/cite&gt; and use that fancy
password to log in for the first time and start the setup wizard; or should I say
butler?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &amp;quot;butler&amp;quot; has completed, it's time to get started with setting up some CI
jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="preparing-a-simple-pytest-job-with-jenkins"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparing a Simple &lt;cite&gt;pytest&lt;/cite&gt; Job with Jenkins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'll caution that I this portion doesn't cover any of the GitLab/Jenkins
interfacing, maybe I'll get to writing that in another article... As part of the
material I'm skipping, I'm going to breeze right over the GitLab connection and
repository information. I'm going to focus, instead, on the build operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;With the new Jenkins server up and running, create a &amp;quot;New Item,&amp;quot; give it a
descriptive, memorable name, and set it as a &amp;quot;Freestyle Project&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Create a new project in Jenkins for CI." src="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/images/jenkins-new-config.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;After configuring the various other settings relevant to the project (repository,
build-triggers, etc.) find the &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Build&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; section and from the &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Add build step&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;
select &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Execute shell&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;In the new &amp;quot;Command&amp;quot; field of the &amp;quot;Execute shell&amp;quot; section, insert the commands
necessary to navigate to the appropriate subdirectory and run &lt;cite&gt;pytest&lt;/cite&gt;. In my case,
my pytest &amp;quot;test folder&amp;quot; is located in the root directory, so I don't really need
to change the working directory; I just go and run &lt;cite&gt;pytest&lt;/cite&gt;. I do run a few other
generic commands just to make sure that I've got a fair report of the build
environment in case I need to go back and debug some things. So, here's a sample
of what my configuration might look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;quot;Current Directory&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;pwd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;quot;List Folder Structure&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;ls -a ./&amp;lt;name-of-my-python-package-folder&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;quot;Run pytest&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;pytest -v&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Jenkins"></category><category term="Gitlab"></category><category term="Raspberry Pi"></category><category term="Dev Ops"></category><category term="GIT"></category><category term="CI/CD"></category></entry><entry><title>pycev - A Python CEV Reader</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/pycev-a-python-cev-reader.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-12T10:59:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T10:59:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-12-12:/stanley-solutions-blog/pycev-a-python-cev-reader.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Another new project? Well, why not? This time, we'll be tackling reading CEV files from SEL in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img alt="Introducing: pycev!" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/engineerjoe440/pycev/main/logo/pycev.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another new project?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. That's right. I'm starting another new project. But hey! There's a lot of framework
that needs to be introduced before I can start doing all the cool high-level stuff that we
all want to see and use. I mean, by now you should understand that I'm all about getting
the framework right. If you're still not sure, go read my rant about getting the framework
right... &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/write-framework-once.html"&gt;This is my rant on getting framework right.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="goal"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goal:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the plan here, anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this project, &lt;cite&gt;pycev&lt;/cite&gt; (I've almost considered that it should be pronounced &amp;quot;pie-safe&amp;quot;, but
that's not how it looks, so we'll let that stew a while longer) will be a package for reading and
interpreting SEL Compressed EVent records. They're a proprietary (but open) format in which SEL
protective relays collect event information and &amp;quot;compress&amp;quot; it into a format that's easily read
by machines (computers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's already a handful of projects out in the wild for reading COMTRADE records; which, if
you're unfamiliar are &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Common Format for Transient Data Exchange&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; files, and are supported by
many SEL relays in addition to a much broader number of other vendor devices. Trouble is, not
everyone uses COMTRADE, and comparatively, CEV files are a little simpler, and (in my opinion)
more straight-forward and robust. Perhaps the best Python project for reading COMTRADE files
is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dparrini/python-comtrade"&gt;Python Comtrade&lt;/a&gt;. That project shows great maturity and value. It also sees regular updates
and bugfixes as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it's such a well respected and mature project, I'd like to take it as inspiration for
&lt;cite&gt;pycev&lt;/cite&gt; and use it to help me realize the best API for the package so that the two libraries
could (potentially) be used interchangeably for various projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-s-first"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's First?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess starting the package development is first!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've already carved out a repository, and I've got something of a skeleton package put together.
I think the first step will be getting enough working that I can upload it to PyPI to reserve
the namespace. Then full development will need to come. There's a good handful of things that
need to be tackled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload Project to PyPI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop Core Functionality and Match API to that of &amp;quot;Python-Comtrade&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop Automated Test Suite with Local Server and Various Existing CEV Files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's the sort of roadmap I see before me. Now, the time-frame is still way up in the air;
so who knows whe this all will &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; happen. But here's hoping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in checking in on the project, and would like to jump in and contribute,
have a little look at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/engineerjoe440/pycev"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;, and feel free to open an &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/engineerjoe440/pycev/issues"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; to start a conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="SEL"></category><category term="CEV"></category><category term="Event"></category><category term="Record"></category><category term="Files"></category><category term="Power System"></category><category term="Analysis"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading Data with selprotopy</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/reading-data-with-selprotopy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-22T19:02:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-22T19:02:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-11-22:/stanley-solutions-blog/reading-data-with-selprotopy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Finally reading some data from SEL relays using Python! Now to get the controls working...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Still deep in the process of getting a fully functional SEL protocol binding suite in Python, but,
hey! At least I can write a little update on what's been going on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(if you haven't read my article on what &lt;cite&gt;selprotopy&lt;/cite&gt; is, take a look &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://blog.stanleysolutionsnw.com/sel-protocol-coming-to-python.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past month of so, I've been able to really &amp;quot;whack out&amp;quot; some reasonable functionality. In
fact, I've been able to poll an SEL-351 for both digital and analog data. For those of you who
are a little familiar with SEL protocol, that means that I've been able to create a parser for
the relay definition block, and the various fast-meter blocks in addition to the DNA definition.
To boot, I've even tested (albeit breifly) on an SEL-751 and saw pretty promissing results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all pretty good, but the eventual goal (well, &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; eventual goal) is to be able to poll
regularly and send commands/controls as needed. I'd also like to be able to read CEV reports
(more on that in the future) and perhaps the relay's SER (Sequential Event Recorder). So, is any
of the control functionality working yet? Not really...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've gotten to the point where the commands &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be configured and sent correctly to the
relay, but no dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere along the lines, I've clearly &amp;quot;bugged&amp;quot; something up. So now, it's really just a matter
of doing some additional debugging. Hmm... will need to get started on that. Trouble is, I've got
lots of other fun projects to work on too!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="c-mon-joe-wrap-this-thing-up"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;C'mon, Joe; wrap this thing up...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I'm rambling; at this point, I'm pretty excited to say that I've got some polling working
with &lt;cite&gt;selprotopy&lt;/cite&gt;, but there's clearly some more to work on. I'm hoping that I can get commands
working here pretty soon, and then I've got a handful of options as the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="i-could"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I could:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a system to read the SER&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the CEV reading figured out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;start testing on a variety of SEL relays (but this would require testing a FOSS project at SEL,
so I'm still not sure about this one)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get an automated test suite built on my local GitLab instance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly some more work coming, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Protocols"></category><category term="SEL"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Communications"></category><category term="Metering"></category></entry><entry><title>Introducing selprotopy</title><link href="https://engineerjoe440.github.io/stanley-solutions-blog/sel-protocol-coming-to-python.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-20T11:07:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T15:45:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Joe Stanley</name></author><id>tag:engineerjoe440.github.io,2020-09-20:/stanley-solutions-blog/sel-protocol-coming-to-python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;The SEL Protocol binding suite for Python is finally coming...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;SEL Protocol is finally coming for Python. That's right, you've heard correctly; it's coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="The new... `selprotopy`!" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/engineerjoe440/sel-proto-py/master/logo/selprotopy.png" style="width: 350px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, what is SEL Protocol anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it's a communications protocol, or standard, that was developed by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://selinc.com/"&gt;SEL&lt;/a&gt; to support
fast data communications between protective electric relays (the devices that monitor the
power grid for faults) and communications processors. It was developed in the early '90s to
help improve communication support of devices to allow users to monitor protective relays
from a distance, and to perform control operations without being present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've begun writing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/engineerjoe440/sel-proto-py"&gt;selprotopy&lt;/a&gt; which will be a protocol driver supporting SEL protocol in
Python. This means that users will be able to integrate solutions with SEL relays using
Python!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, there's a lot to come, so this is not much more than an early announcement.
If you're interested in contributing, feel free to drop me a message! I'd love to interact!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Protocols"></category><category term="SEL"></category></entry></feed>